<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://wyzhao23.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://wyzhao23.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-31T06:00:43+00:00</updated><id>https://wyzhao23.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal website of Wenyuan (Warren) Zhao. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Bayesian Deep Learning as Deep Gaussian Processes</title><link href="https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2025/deep-bayesian-learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bayesian Deep Learning as Deep Gaussian Processes"/><published>2025-01-21T11:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-21T11:46:00+00:00</updated><id>https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2025/deep-bayesian-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2025/deep-bayesian-learning/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="deep-additive-kernel-learning">Deep Additive Kernel Learning</h2> <p>With the strengths of both deep learning and kernel methods like Gaussian Processes (GPs), Deep Kernel Learning (DKL) has gained considerable attention in recent years. From the computational perspective, however, DKL becomes challenging when the input dimension of the last-layer GP is high. To address this challenge, we propose the Deep Additive Kernel (DAK) model, which incorporates i) an additive structure for the last-layer GP; and ii) induced prior approximation for each GP component. This naturally leads to a last-layer Bayesian neural network (BNN) architecture. The proposed method enjoys the interpretability of DKL as well as the computational advantages of BNN. Empirical results show that the proposed approach outperforms state-of-the-art DKL methods in both regression and classification tasks.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/dak-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/dak-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/dak-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/dak.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Check our latest paper:</p> <ul> <li>AISTATS 2025: From deep additive kernel learning to last-layer Bayesian neural networks via induced prior approximation</li> </ul> <h2 id="deep-markov-gaussian-processes">Deep Markov Gaussian Processes</h2> <p>Deep Gaussian Processes (DGPs) are a powerful class of probabilistic models that extend traditional GPs by stacking multiple GP layers. We develop software based on a class of DGPs with sparse structure, referred to as Deep Markov GPs (DMGPs). More specifically, we implement DMGPs as sparsely activated Bayesian Neural Networks (BNNs) with learnable weights and biases, which can be used in a wide range of deep learning applications. The depth of DGPs enables them to model intricate dependencies and variations, making them suitable for tasks such as regression, classification, and time-series analysis. The DMGP software can provide not only uncertainty quantification for predictions, but also interpretability by incorporating the neural additive structure. Our evaluation across various tabular datasets and visual object tasks shows that DMGPs not only match but often surpasses the performance of traditional DGP methods, all while significantly reducing the number of parameters. Due to the strong connection to deep neural networks, DMGPs can be easily extended to other state-of-art deep learning architectures and applications.</p> <p>DMGP package is available at <a href="https://github.com/warrenzha/dmgp">https://github.com/warrenzha/dmgp</a>.</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://dmgp.readthedocs.io">Documentation, examples, tutorials</a> on how to construct all sorts of DMGP models.</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/tmgp-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/tmgp-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/tmgp-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/tmgp.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="machine-learning"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Deep Neural Networks (DNNs) are powerful tools capable of capturing intricate patterns in large datasets, but lack the ability to provide uncertainty estimation. To learn rich, hierarchical representations from data with proper interpretability and uncertainty estimation, efficient Bayesian deep learning gain considerable attention in a variety of real-world tasks, especially when uncertainty quantification is critical.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Private Information Retrieval</title><link href="https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2024/weakly-pir/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Private Information Retrieval"/><published>2024-01-15T11:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-15T11:46:00+00:00</updated><id>https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2024/weakly-pir</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2024/weakly-pir/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="leaky-private-information-retrieval">Leaky Private Information Retrieval</h2> <p>We study the problem of leaky private information retrieval (L-PIR), where the amount of privacy leakage is measured by the pure differential privacy parameter, referred to as the leakage ratio exponent. Unlike the previous L-PIR scheme proposed by Samy et al., which only adjusted the probability allocation to the clean (low-cost) retrieval pattern, we optimize the probabilities assigned to all the retrieval patterns jointly. It is demonstrated that the optimal retrieval pattern probability distribution is quite sophisticated and has a layered structure: the retrieval patterns associated with the random key values of lower Hamming weights should be assigned higher probabilities. This new scheme provides a significant improvement, leading to an O(log K) leakage ratio exponent with fixed download cost D and number of servers N, in contrast to the previous art that only achieves a Θ(K) exponent, where K is the number of messages.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/wpir-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/wpir-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/wpir-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/wpir.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/pirdp-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/pirdp-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/pirdp-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/pirdp.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="weakly-private-information-retrieval">Weakly Private Information Retrieval</h2> <p>Private information retrieval (PIR) systems were motivated by the necessity to safeguard user privacy during information retrieval. In the standard PIR framework, a user wishes to retrieve a desired message from N non-colluding servers efficiently, such that the identity of the desired message is not leaked in a significant manner. We study the problem of weakly PIR when there is heterogeneity in servers’ trustfulness, i.e. some servers can be more trustworthy than others, under the maximal leakage (Max-L) metric and mutual information (MI) metric. A code construction is proposed for this setting and optimized the probability distribution for this construction.</p> <p>Check our latest paper:</p> <ul> <li><strong>ISIT 2024</strong>: <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.17940">Weakly Private Information Retrieval from Heterogeneously Trusted Servers</a></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="information-theory"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Private information retrieval (PIR) systems are motivated by the necessity to safeguard user privacy during information retrieval. In the canonical PIR framework, a user wishes to retrieve a message from N independent servers, each holding a complete set of K messages. The message’s identity must remain hidden from any individual server. This privacy requirement necessarily incurs higher download costs than a protocol without such a requirement, which requires effort to improve the code construction of PIR systems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI-driven Dynamic mmWave Networking</title><link href="https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2023/mmwave-networking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI-driven Dynamic mmWave Networking"/><published>2023-06-15T11:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-15T11:46:00+00:00</updated><id>https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2023/mmwave-networking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2023/mmwave-networking/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="dynamic-mmwave-mesh-network">Dynamic mmWave Mesh Network</h2> <p>Millimeter-wavelength (mmWave) mesh network can provide multi-Gbps transmission but with large path loss and heterogeneous objectives which is hard to solve by heuristic models. Machine learning (ML) techniques, especially reinforcement learning (RL), have great potential in solving multi-objective, non-linear, and non-convex problems that often happen in mmWave mesh network configuration. On the other hand, network configuration policies learned from simulations cannot always help physical networks meet performance requirements due to sim2real gap. In this work, we develop a reinforcement learning (RL) model to train a policy for dynamic topology management and a self-supervised policy adaptation algorithm to bridge the domain gap. The experimental results shows that our RL agent can learn a policy to avoid blockage links and self-supervised learning model can help to eliminate domain gaps. The testbed we built can establish multiple routes and can be controlled effectively by a central controller. We successfully ran the simulation-trained RL policy and self-supervision agent on the real testbed.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/dymesh-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/dymesh-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/dymesh-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/dymesh.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="communications"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Integrated Access and Backhaul (IAB) is an emerging technique to enable cost-effective deployment of dense 5G networks that utilize emerging millimeter-wavelength (mmWave) spectrum. Existing heuristic-based network control/management frameworks are not well-suited for the increasing complexity and uncertainty introduced by mmWave IAB. Machine learning (ML) can help automate network control decisions, but its practical deployment faces new system-level challenges in 5G IAB, including accurate simulation-based training, resolving conflicting objectives from heterogeneous network slices, and efficiently collecting observations for run-time decision-making.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Machine Learning and Data Science</title><link href="https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2021/machine-learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Machine Learning and Data Science"/><published>2021-06-15T11:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-15T11:46:00+00:00</updated><id>https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2021/machine-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2021/machine-learning/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="ml-based-matrix-optimization-in-massive-mimo">ML-based Matrix Optimization in Massive MIMO</h2> <p>In the downlink of massive MIMO, the transmitter uses precoding technology to reduce interference and improve spectrum efficiency. A complex-valued gradient neural network (CVGNN) is proposed to solve the Moore-Penrose inverse of the complex matrix in massive MIMO precoding algorithms. Theoretical linear convergence and numerical results are provided to corroborate the application of CVGNN in wireless communication senarios.</p> <h2 id="fog-computing-in-internet-of-vehicles">Fog Computing in Internet of Vehicles</h2> <p>As the technology of network, wireless transmission and big data computing develops rapidly, the society has entered the Information Era. Internet of Vehicles, the important part of the Internet of Things, is the inevitable trend of urban traffic in the future. Fog computing emerges as a new technology of distributed computing, which is suitable for applications in the Internet of Vehicles. Internet of Vehicles based on fog computing can solve the problems of traffic congestion, transportation efficiency and security. In this paper, we review the recent work in this topic and analyze the architecture and scenario of fog computing in the Internet of Vehicles. Three aspects of applications are proposed in this paper: VANET, big data processing and security. At the same time, we discuss the technical details and challenges in these applications. Fog computing has excellent processing power in real-time big data and a high mobility environment, which reduces the latency of data processing, makes the deployment between vehicles and roadside units more reasonable and enhances the security of information interchanged in the Internet of Vehicles. Fog computing devices will become an indispensable part of the future construction of Internet of Vehicles.</p> <p>“A Survey on Fog Computing Applications in Internet of Vehicles”, International Conference on Computing and Data Science, 2021.</p> <h2 id="online-review-classifier">Online Review Classifier</h2> <p>Customer reviews on e-commerce platforms contain valuable information, while sifting through them manually tends to dismay people because of the huge amount of data. This study implemented a machine learning-based algorithm to classify customer reviews. Our classifier extracts Chinese word segmentation and text frequency for feature extraction and scoring, and implements the classification with methods of Naive Bayesian and Support Vector Machines. Experimental results on the Taobao product review sentiment datasets show that our model based on two machine learning algorithms, though results in different performances, can provide suggestions on the selection of the identification classifier using a trade-off strategy and helps obtain fast and accurate classification on reviews of different categories.</p> <p>“<a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1742-6596/1678/1/012081/pdf">Classification of Customer Reviews on E-commerce Platforms Based on Naive Bayesian Algorithm and Support Vector Machine</a>”</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="machine-learning"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We studied the general area of machine learning and data science. A machine learning-based algorithm is proposed to classify customer reviews. A complex-valued gradient neural network (CVGNN) is proposed to solve the Moore-Penrose inverse of complex matrices. We also investigated fog computing in the Internet of Vehicles.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">mmWave Beamforming</title><link href="https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2020/beamforming/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="mmWave Beamforming"/><published>2020-06-15T11:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-15T11:46:00+00:00</updated><id>https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2020/beamforming</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wyzhao23.github.io/blog/2020/beamforming/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="beam-alignment-and-tracking">Beam Alignment and Tracking</h2> <p>Millimeter wave (mmwave) communications have attracted increasing attention thanks to the abundant spectrum resource. The short wave-length of mmwave signals facilitates exploiting large antenna arrays to achieve large array gains and combat large path-loss. However, the use of large antenna arrays along with narrow beams leads to a large overhead in beam training for obtaining channel state information, especially in dynamic environments. To reduce the overhead of beam training, in this paper we formulate the problem of beam alignment and tracking (BA/T) as a stochastic bandit problem. In particular, to sense the change of the environments, the actions are designed based on the offset of successive beam indexes (i.e., beam index difference), which measures the rate of change of the environments. Then, we propose two efficient BA/T algorithms based on the stochastic bandit learning. To reveal useful insights, the performance of effective achievable rate is further analyzed for the proposed BA/T algorithms. The analytical results show that the algorithms can sense the change of the environments and adjust beam training strategies intelligently. In addition, they do not require any priori knowledge of dynamic channel modeling, and thus are applicable to a variety of complicated scenarios. Simulation results demonstrate the effectiveness and superiority of the proposed algorithms.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/bat-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/bat-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/bat-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/bat.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="communications"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The short wave-length of mmwave signals facilitates exploiting large antenna arrays to achieve large array gains and combat large path-loss. However, the use of large antenna arrays along with narrow beams leads to a large overhead in beam training for obtaining channel state information, especially in dynamic environments.]]></summary></entry></feed>